Guide to the Dick Thornburgh Papers, 1932- AIS.1998.30.07
ULS Archives & Special Collections
- United States Attorney for Western Pennsylvania, 1969-1975; VII.
  - News Releases, 2.
    - April-June, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 5)
      - Former City Alderman Frank Bruno will be arraigned on charges of obstructing the enforcement of the PA anti-gambling laws, April, 1974; 12.
      - Thornburgh charged Houghland Barge Line, Inc., with a failure to promptly report to the U.S. Coast Guard an oil spill at Midland, PA, April 26, 1974; 13.
      - A former Pittsburgh labor leader was convicted in U.S. District Court of embezzling union funds, May 3, 1974; 14.
      - The former Chief of Police in North Versailles Township is scheduled to commence a thirty-day federal prison sentence, May 6, 1974; 15.
      - Petitions have been filed seeking the jailing of Robert Iannelli and Michael Masullo for violating terms of their release, May, 1974; 16.
      - A former Allegheny County Detective was indicted on charges of accepting payoffs from local racket interests, May 16, 1974; 17.
      - A federal grand jury returned a six-count indictment charging the owner of three of Pittsburgh's Liberty Avenue adult theatres with the interstate transportation of pornographic films, May 17, 1974; 18.
      - A federal grand jury indicted Harry H. Jessup on four counts of income tax evasion, May 17, 1974; 19.
      - A federal grand jury returned a two-count indictment charging a former U.S. Customs Port Director with embezzling over $9,000 in customs duties, May 17, 1974; 20.
      - A federal grand jury returned indictments charging two former managers of the Hollidaysburg Trust Company with embezzling more than $35,000 of the funds of that bank, May 17, 1974; 21.
      - A federal grand jury indicted seven persons on charges of defrauding the Oakland Veterans' Administration Hospital of over $11,000, May 17, 1974; 22.
      - Federal prosecutors initiated a third court action aimed at jailing another Pittsburgh area gambling figure previously convicted of violating the Organized Crime Control Act of 1970, May 23, 1974; 23.
      - Racket gambling kingpins in Western PA are finding that federal law enforcement efforts mean more than a slap on the wrist, May 30, 1974; 24.
      - Budd Rice pleaded guilty to income tax evasion charges for the year 1969, June 3, 1974; 25.
      - The U.S. Court of Appeals upheld the conviction of Samuel Ferraro on charges related to the receipt of over $300,000 in protection payoffs from area racket figures, June 6, 1973; 26.
      - The U.S. Court of Appeals upheld an order jailing racket boss Michael Genovese for contempt for refusing to answer questions, June 6, 1974; 27.
      - Convicted Pittsburgh area bookmaker Robert Iannelli has been ordered to commence a three-year jail term, June 10, 1974; 28.
      - Federal Postal Inspectors arrested an Ohio man in connection with a scheme to collect money for tickets to a bogus outdoor rock concert, June 12, 1974; 29.
      - Seven Pittsburghers were indicted by a special federal grand jury on charges relating to conduct of a large scale illegal sports bookmaking business, June 13, 1974; 30.
      - Thornburgh confirmed that he has issued grand jury subpoenas to the three individuals identified last week as payoff collectors for the Allegheny County Sheriff, June 26, 1974; 31.
      - A federal grand jury indicted two former officials of the Westinghouse Electric Corporation Salaried Employees Union on charges of embezzling $66,000 from the Union, July 9, 1974; 32.
    - July-September, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 6)
      - A federal grand jury indicted two former officials of the Westinghouse Electric Corporation Salaried Employees Union on charges of embezzling $66,000 from the Union, July 9, 1974; 1.
      - An Erie man was indicted on bankruptcy fraud charges in connection with the concealment of over $30,000 of merchandise, July 11, 1974; 2.
      - A federal grand jury indicted Dr. Robert Penman on charges of willful failure to file income tax returns, July 11, 1974; 3.
      - A federal grand jury returned an eight count indictment against attorney James Ashton on charges of mail fraud and criminal contempt of court, July 12, 1974; 4.
      - Thornburgh will speak to a dinner meeting of the McKeesport Bar Association on Thursday, July 18, 1974; 5.
      - A Johnstown businessman was sentenced to 10 days imprisonment and fined a total of $12,000 on charges of attempted income tax evasion, July 23, 1974; 6.
      - A Somerset businessman was fined $1,000 and placed on probation for 2 years for failing to account for taxes withheld from the wages of his employees, July 24, 1974; 7.
      - Thornburgh announced the appointment of James J. West as an Assistant United States Attorney, August 12, 1974; 8.
      - A Pittsburgh couple were given suspended prison sentences of one year on charges of filing false income tax returns, August 20, 1974; 9.
      - Twenty persons were indicted by a federal grand jury for their participation in the multi-million dollar numbers gambling operation headed by Nicholas Terleski, August 22, 1974; 10.
      - David M. Curry and Jay C. Waldman, two Assistant U.S. Attorneys in the Thornburgh's office, have been presented with Special Achievement Awards by Attorney General William B. Saxbe, August, 1974; 11.
      - Thornburgh announced that the special federal grand jury investigating organized crime and official corruption in the Erie area, will reconvene in September, August 26, 1974; 12.
      - Three men were arrested by federal marshals on charges of obstructing navigation at the West Penn Power Company's Mitchell Station in Washington County, August 26, 1974; 13.
      - The federal special grand jury investigating organized crime and racketeering returned its first indictment under the 1970 Federal Organized Crime Control Act, August 27, 1974; 14.
      - Former McKeesport City Councilman, Michael J. Newman, surrendered to agents of the ATF on charges of illegal possession of firearms, September 13, 1974; 15.
      - The former Allegheny County "Racket Squad" Chief will report to the federal penitentiary at Lewisburg to begin a six year jail term, September 16, 1974; 16.
      - The president of the Federation of Westinghouse Independent Salaried Employees Union was charged with two counts of making false statements in Union books, September 16, 1974; 17.
      - Thornburgh will testify before the House Judiciary Committee's Special Sub-Committee on Reform of federal Criminal Laws in Washington, D.C., September 17, 1974; 18.
      - Thornburgh announced that the special federal grand jury on investigating organized crime and official corruption in the Erie area, will reconvene, September 18, 1974; 19.
      - A federal grand jury indicted David B. Adams for willful failure to file income tax returns, September 18, 1974; 20.
      - A former official of the Federation of Westinghouse Electric Corporation Independent Salaried Employees Union pleaded guilty to ten counts of embezzling funds, September 23, 1974; 21.
      - Allegations of leaks from the federal grand jury concerning the testimony of former PA Secretary of Property and Supplies are nonsense, September 24, 1974; 22.
    - October-December, 1974 (Box 35, Folder 7)
      - A federal grand jury indicted Frank C. Hilton on perjury charges, October 10, 1974; 1.
      - A federal grand jury indicted two men on charges of engineering a $700,000 fraud scheme, October 10, 1974; 2.
      - A Clairton man was sentenced in federal court for failing to register with the Selective Service System, October 11, 1974; 3.
      - PA State Senator Frank Mazzei was indicted by a federal grand jury on two counts of extortion, October 24, 1974; 4.
      - A federal court jury convicted a major supplier of Canadian-manufactured methamphetamine, November 1, 1974; 5.
      - A fruit grower was sentenced in federal court to serve 60 days in prison on charges of income tax evasion, November 6, 1974; 6.
      - Thornburgh filed criminal charges against Pennsylvania Industrial Chemical Corporation alleging violations of the federal water pollution control laws, November 6, 1974; 7.
      - Frank C. Hilton will be arraigned tomorrow on perjury charges, November 6, 1974; 8.
      - The proprietor of the White Power Book Store in Wilkinsburg was indicted on two counts of violation of the federal firearms laws, November 8, 1974; 9.
      - A federal court jury returned landmark guilty verdicts against the owner of 3 of Pittsburgh's adult theatres on charges of interstate transportation of pornographic films, November 19, 1974; 10.
      - A federal court jury returned a guilty verdict against an area man charged with pirating a trade secret worth $12 million from his employer, November 25, 1974; 11.
      - A federal court jury convicted Senator Frank Mazzei on two counts of extortion under the federal Hobbs Anti-Racketeering Act, November 26, 1974; 12.
      - Another former member of the Allegheny County Detective Bureau "Racket Squad" pleaded guilty to charges of accepting protection payoffs, December 4, 1974; 13.
      - A federal grand jury indicted two men on charges of illegal wiretapping, December 4, 1974; 14.
      - A federal court jury returned a guilty verdict against 6 individuals charged with involvement in an interstate narcotics distribution ring, December 6, 1974; 15.
      - Daniel H. Shapira will be sworn in as an Assistant U.S. Attorney tomorrow, December 8, 1974; 16.
      - A major supplier to the area of Canadian-manufactured methamphetamine was sentenced to eight years imprisonment, December 16, 1974; 17.
      - A special federal grand jury returned a three-count indictment against five individuals charged with involvement in an interstate prostitution ring, December 19, 1974; 18.
      - Thornburgh announced that several Pittsburgh area automobile dealers will be brought to court for fraudulently misrepresenting the mileage on cars they have sold, December 20, 1974; 19.
    - January-March, 1975 (Box 35, Folder 8)
      - Pennsylvania Industrial Chemical Corporation has been fined for the second time for violating federal water pollution control laws, January 2, 1975; 1.
      - A federal court jury convicted Domenic Gullia of two counts of perjury, January 8, 1975; 2.
      - Houghland Barge Line, Inc., a Kentucky corporation, was fined for violating federal water pollution control laws, January 9, 1975; 3.
      - Seventeen Pittsburgh area residents were indicted for seeking to defraud auto insurance companies, January 10, 1975; 4.
      - The owner of three of Pittsburgh's adult theatres was sentenced to six months imprisonment, January 16, 1975; 5.
      - Time is running out for men who deserted from the Armed Forces or violated the Selective Service Laws during the Vietnam era to avoid prosecution by taking advantage of President Ford's Amnesty Program, January 17, 1975; 6.
      - A federal court jury returned a guilty verdict against a former U.S. Customs Port Director on two counts of embezzlement, January 17, 1975; 7.
      - A McKeesport automobile dealer received a five year sentence in federal court in connection with his participation in an interstate car theft, January 21, 1975; 8.
      - A federal court jury convicted Pittsburgh Constable Pronty Ford of accepting cash protection payoffs, January 23, 1975; 9.
      - A forty-nine count indictment charging conspiracy to defraud Butler area purchasers of used automobiles was returned today, January 28, 1975; 10.
      - A special grand jury returned a 15 count indictment charging three area individuals with conspiring to commit arson and insurance fraud, January 28, 1975; 11.
      - A federal court jury returned a guilty verdict against Harry Jessup on charges of income tax evasion, February 13, 1975; 12.
      - Thornburgh and Assistant U. S. Attorney Blair A. Griffith will be in Philadelphia to participate in a program on "Investigation and Prosecution of Corruption in Government.", February 20, 1975; 13.
      - A special federal grand jury returned an indictment against six area men for conducting a large-scale sports gambling operation, February 20, 1975; 14.
      - A federal grand jury indicted three Pittsburgh men on charges of violating the federal Hobbs Anti-Racketeering Statute, February 26, 1975; 15.
      - A federal grand jury returned a sealed indictment against nine persons charged with operating a large-scale numbers gambling operation, February 27, 1975; 16.
      - A federal grand jury returned a nine-count indictment against Max H. Homer, charging him with extortion, obstruction of justice, perjury and income tax fraud, February 27, 1975; 17.
      - A federal grand jury returned indictments against three North Braddock Borough Councilmen and a Duquesne contractor for bribes and kickbacks, February 27, 1975; 18.
      - Chief Judge Rabe F. Marsh will hear arguments on motions for a new trial and a directed verdict of acquittal file on behalf of Senator Frank Mazzei, February 27, 1975; 19.
      - A federal grand jury returned a sealed indictment against fourteen persons charged with operating a large-scale numbers gambling operation, March 3, 1975; 20.
      - A former U.S. Customs Service official received a five year prison sentence upon his conviction for embezzling federal funds, March 6, 1975; 21.
      - A federal grand jury indicted Frank C. Hilton on charges of perjury, extortion and income tax fraud, March 12, 1975; 22.
      - Thornburgh will testify before the House Judiciary Committee's Special Sub-Committee on Reform of Federal Criminal Laws in Washington, D.C, March 24, 1975; 23.
      - An East Liberty man was sentenced to serve 60 days in prison on his perjury conviction growing out of testimony in a federal court trial, March 24, 1975; 24.
      - A Clarion County couple was indicted for tax evasion and filing false income tax returns, March 26, 1975; 25.
      - A federal grand jury indicted two Pittsburgh area gambling figures for tax fraud, March 26, 1975; 26.
      - Dr. Robert Penman was indicted for willfully making a false statement to the U.S. District Court at his sentencing on a prior tax conviction, March 26, 1975; 27.
      - A former Secretary-Treasurer of Local 3 of the International Association of Bridge, Structural and Ornamental Iron Workers was sentenced today for embezzlement, March 26, 1975; 28.
      - Thornburgh filed an appeal from an order staying federal grand jury proceedings involving the Clairton Coke Works of the U.S. Steel Corporation, March 26, 1975; 29.
      - Thornburgh has been selected as a Fellow of the American Bar Foundation, March, 1975; 30
    - May-July, 1975 (Box 35, Folder 9)
      - Four Pittsburgh area residents were indicted on charges that they possessed and sold counterfeit coins, May 9, 1975; 1.
      - Nicholas Gobos entered a plea of guilty in court to a three-count indictment on tax evasion, May 13, 1975; 2.
      - The first forgery and passing of a federal income tax rebate check was uncovered by agents of the Secret Service and Post Inspection Service, with the arrest of a Pittsburgh man, May 23, 1975; 3.
      - A former New York attorney pleaded guilty to charges of engineering an interstate fraud scheme, May 27, 1975; 4.
      - Senator Frank Mazzei was indicted by a federal grand jury on perjury charges, June 3, 1975; 5.
      - A federal grand jury indicted a practicing ophthalmologist on income tax fraud charges, June 5, 1975; 6.
      - A federal grand jury indicted a former Allegheny County Deputy Sheriff and Frank Bruno on charges of conspiring to obstruct the enforcement of PA's gambling laws, June 5, 1975; 7.
      - James Martorella was sentenced to 3 years imprisonment on a charge of tax evasion, June 16, 1975; 8.
      - A federal grand jury returned an 11 count indictment charging 14 men with various violations of federal racketeering and gambling statutes, June 17, 1975; 9.
      - Twelve additional persons were indicted on federal charges in connection with the operation of an illegal gambling business, June 19, 1975; 10.
      - Thornburgh announced the filing of federal actions against five auto dealers for selling automobiles with rolled-back odometers, June 24, 1975; 11.
      - U.S. District Judge William W. Knox sentenced a doctor to 60 days in jail for failing to file an income tax return on gross income, June 30, 1975; 12.
      - Thornburgh will be sworn in as Assistant Attorney General in charge of the Criminal Division of the U.S. Department of Justice on July 8, 1975, July, 1975; 13.
    - Press Releases: Allegheny County Detectives, 1971 - 1973 (Box 35, Folder 10)
  - Public Statements, 3.
    The public statements are arranged chronologically and titles consist of a brief summary of the content. These statements contain policy and issue information, and relate to programs and actions of the Office of the U.S. Attorney. Topics include, for example: organized crime, narcotics and dangerous drugs, official corruption, actions of the strike forces, and the criminal justice system. These public statements relate in content and format to the news releases both of which are available here online.
    - 1969 (Box 36, Folder 1)
      - Thornburgh forecast a substantial increase in federal action against big-time distributors of narcotics and dangerous drugs, August 6, 1969; 1.
      - Narcotics and dangerous drugs: the federal approach, September, 1969; 2.
      - Thornburgh predicted that the U.S. Supreme Court is entering an era of refinement, September 17, 1969; 3.
      - Thornburgh reviewed the results of what he called a highly successful criminal term in federal court, October 22, 1969; 4.
      - Statement for the Pennsylvania Crime Commission before the Allegheny Commissioners, November 20, 1969; 5.
      - Thornburgh called for citizen support of the Nixon Administration's proposed changes in the federal laws relating to narcotics and dangerous drugs, November 24, 1969; 6.
    - 1970 (Box 36, Folder 2)
      - Thornburgh termed much of the educational emphasis in the field of narcotics and dangerous drugs to be misguided, January 15, 1970; 1.
      - "Organized crime and street crime go hand in hand," said Thornburgh at a meeting of the Allegheny County Lawyer Wives, February 19, 1970; 2.
      - "Organized crime and street crime go hand in hand\," said Thornburgh to the Women's Conference on Organized Crime, March 17, 1970; 3.
      - Thornburgh praised federal law agencies for what he termed a superior performance in the effort against crime in Western Pennsylvania, March 26, 1970; 4.
      - Thornburgh told a luncheon meeting of the Lions Club of Pittsburgh that organized crime and the official corruption that accompanies it are the truly subversive elements in this country, April 22, 1970; 5.
      - Thornburgh characterized "ignorance as one of the greatest stumbling blocks in the fight against drug abuse in this country" at a training session for North Hills law enforcement officials., May 22, 1970; 6.
      - Massive federal efforts against illicit trafficking in narcotics and dangerous drugs are beginning to take hold, July 27, 1970; 7.
      - The Nixon Administration's Anti-Organized Crime Bill is a must to deal with syndicated gambling operations in Allegheny County, August 11, 1970; 8.
      - Thornburgh called for legislation authorizing special federal grand juries to issue public reports on misconduct by public officials in connection with organized crime, September 10, 1970; 9.
      - Thornburgh warned members of the Greensburg Rotary Club against the threat of organized crime to legitimate business, September 29, 1970; 10.
      - Thornburgh outlined efforts against distributors of narcotics and dangerous drugs at a meeting of the Kiwanis Club, October 1, 1970; 11.
      - Bail pending appeal for convicted criminal defendants who have attempted to harm government witnesses will be resisted, October 2, 1970; 12.
      - Disclosures of lottery fixes are only further indications of the cost the community must bear for illegal gambling operations, October 6, 1970; 13.
      - Thornburgh called for massive educational undertaking in the field of narcotics and dangerous drugs, October 21, 1970; 14.
      - Thornburgh predicted a much more aggressive approach by federal authorities toward pollution of navigable waters, November 17, 1970; 16.
      - Federal anti-crime efforts in Western Pennsylvania will be stepped up considerably during 1971, December 30, 1970; 17.
    - 1971 (Box 36, Folder 3)
      - New federal weapons against organized crime's syndicated gambling operations and corruption of local law enforcement officials will be unveiled in Western Pennsylvania in 1971, January 14, 1971; 1.
      - Thornburgh promised an all out federal effort against the 'politico-racket complex' in Western Pennsylvania, February 28, 1971; 2.
      - Federal revenue-sharing in the criminal justice area is already under way, March 4, 1971; 3.
      - Federal efforts against labor racketeering in Western Pennsylvania will be stepped up in the near future, March 9, 1971; 4.
      - "Organized crime and street crime go hand in had in Pittsburgh as elsewhere," Thornburgh told a meeting at Rodef Shalom Temple, March 16, 1971
      - 52nd anniversary dinner meeting of the Burt Foster Post no. 361, American Legion in McKeesport, March 20, 1971; 5.
      - A 100% federal effort against organized crime is now under way in Western Pennsylvania, March 25, 1971; 6.
      - Illegal gambling is the 'cash register' for all organized crime operations and grosses an estimated $40 million per year in Allegheny County alone, March 31, 1971; 7.
      - Businessmen who ignore the threat of organized crime do so at their peril, April 20, 1971; 8.
      - Today's policeman needs more and better legal device if he is to increase his crime-fighting capacity, April 27, 1971; 9.
      - Thornburgh called for a massive increase in professionalism in the criminal justice system, May 4, 1971; 10.
      - Disclosures of alleged alliances between illegal gambling interests and public officials in Western Pennsylvania communities may only be the tip of the iceberg, May 6, 1971; 11.
      - Federal efforts against organized traffic of narcotics and dangerous drugs are making substantial progress, May 13, 1971; 12.
      - Traffic in hard narcotics is the most organized of the ventures financed and managed by organized crime syndicates, June 14, 1971; 13.
      - Corrupt law enforcement officials can undermine a community almost as effectively as the criminal element, August 5, 1971; 14.
      - Letter from Thornburgh to the Honorable James W. Knepper, Jr., member of the Pennsylvania House of Representatives, regarding legalized gambling, August 16, 1971; 15.
      - Disorganized police cannot deal effectively with organized crime, September 22, 1971; 16.
      - Thornburgh defended the action of bounty hunters in water pollution cases prosecuted by his office under the 1899 Refuse Act, September 27, 1971; 17.
      - The federal government's war against official corruption in Western Pennsylvania has only just begun, October 29, 1971; 18.
      - Stepped-up federal efforts against large scale illegal gambling syndicates are not part of some moral crusade, November 10, 1971; 19.
      - Recent investigations of corruption-ridden local governments have revealed the specific techniques utilized by organized crime syndicates to neutralize Pennsylvania's anti-gambling laws, November 29, 1971; 20.
    - 1972 (Box 36, Folder 4)
      - Pennsylvania's new state lottery will have little or no effect on organized crime's multi-million dollar illegal gambling enterprises, January 11, 1972; 1.